<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter from a gentleman in Ireland to his friend in London upon occasion of a pamphlet entituled a vindication of the present government of Ireland under His Excellency Richard Earl of Tyrconnel.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47993</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1386</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R30938</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11731809</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11731809</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48395</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47993)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48395)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1486:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter from a gentleman in Ireland to his friend in London upon occasion of a pamphlet entituled a vindication of the present government of Ireland under His Excellency Richard Earl of Tyrconnel.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"I shall prove, that it has been, and still is the advantage ... that Ireland should be govern'd by an Englishman" -- p. 2.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tyrconnel, Richard Talbot, --  Earl of, 1630-1691.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  James II, 1685-1688.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  Politics and government --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48395:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER FROM A Gentleman in <hi>IRELAND,</hi> TO His Friend in <hi>LONDON,</hi> Upon Occaſion of a PAMPHLET ENTITULED A VINDICATION Of the Preſent <hi>Government of Ireland</hi> Under his Excellency <hi>Richard</hi> Earl of <hi>TYRCONNEL.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dublin: <hi>Printed in the Year</hi> 1688. <hi>Price Two pence.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:48395:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48395:2"/>
            <head>A LETTER From a Gentleman in <hi>IRELAND,</hi> To His Friend in <hi>LONDON,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS ſoon as the Letter In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>A Vindication of the Preſent Government of</hi> Ireland, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> came to my hands, I ſet upon Anſwering it with the ſame expedition, and plainneſs of Style, as uſes to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company naked Truth, which needs not the cloathing of ſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Arguments, or florid Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to recommend it to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prejudic'd part of Mankind: And indeed upon the very firſt reading of every Paragraph of it, the ſlightneſs of the Arguing, or the notorious Falſhood of the matter of Fact, did ſo evidently appear, that a man of ordinary capacity needs not put his natural talent on the Rack to refute them.</p>
            <p>The very firſt poſition of the Paper, <hi>viz.</hi> [That <hi>Ireland</hi> is in a better way of Thriving under the Government of a Native, than an <hi>Engliſh-man;</hi>] (by which, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, you mean one not barely ſo by Birth, but by Inclination, Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, Education, Religion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) is ſo falſe, that it contradicts the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience and Reaſon of Mankind, and diſguſts one ſo much in the front of the Letter, that I was tempted to fling it away unread, judging it not worth the loſs of ſo much time, if the reſt ſhould prove of the ſame kind (as indeed
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:48395:3"/>I found it upon peruſal); but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ventured through it, I look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon my ſelf obliged to ſay ſomething by way of Anſwer, ſince in the opinion of ſome ſort of men, the not Anſwering (though even the moſt trifling Pamphlet) is given out to be the Inability of the Party to reply to the weight of ſuch Arguments as are contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in it.</p>
            <p>I will not inſiſt much upon the conſtant Practice of all the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſours of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Kings, and their Counſellors, ever ſince the Conqueſt of <hi>Ireland,</hi> who made it an eſtabliſht Maxim, in relation to that Kingdom, that none but an <hi>Engliſh-man</hi> ſhould be chief Governour; inſomuch that (till within theſe two Years) that Practice gave occaſion to the common erronious opinion, That a man born in <hi>Ireland,</hi> however otherwiſe qualified, was thereby incapacitated from being Lord Deputy: It is certain, that long before the Reformation, when matters of Religion made no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction between the Natives of each Country, this was the ſetled and unalter'd Rule: Have we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reaſon then to alter it (now that Religion is put into the Scale, and become the additional weight, which never fails giving the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to the ſide it eſpouſes and adheres to) or raſhly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the wiſe Proceedings of the Anceſtours of Our Kings, and (contrary to the Opinion of the World) judge our Author's <hi>Iriſh</hi> Underſtanding, better than all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ones that have been here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore?</p>
            <p>Our Author will certainly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>Ireland</hi> to be a conqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>'d Country, and conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>quently that the Conquerours have right to eſtabliſh Laws with ſuch reſtricti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and limitations, as ſhall ſeem fitting and convenient towards the keeping it in their hands, and the welfare of the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants; which are of two ſorts, the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Planters, and the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives. I ſhall prove, that it has been, and ſtill is the Advantage of both theſe, that <hi>Ireland</hi> ſhould be Govern'd by an <hi>Engliſh-man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the way, I would have it underſtood, that I do not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to put theſe two Intereſts into any ballance: I know the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Intereſt does ſo far out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weigh the other, that it were a wrong done it, to bring them into any competition; more than two parts of three of the Lands of <hi>Ireland,</hi> being (by the ſeveral Rebellions of the <hi>Iriſh</hi>) in <hi>Britiſh</hi> hands; and for the Quality, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, Induſtry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> there is no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon: beſides, that if one of two Parties is to be pleaſed (thô by the detriment of the other) 'tis but juſt, that the Conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours (who have right to give Law) ſhould be indulg'd: how much more when it is conſiſtent
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:48395:3"/>with the welfare of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, if they underſtood their own good?</p>
            <p>I am convinc'd, that whatever has been done in favour of the Natives, is pure Grace, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be claimed as a juſt Debt, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny otherwiſe than ſince it has been confirmed by Our Laws, and Acts of Parliament: He that reflects on 1641, will readily aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to this, which makes me ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire at the pertneſs of our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor in Capitulating, as if we ſtood upon even ground with them; but 'tis plain, he conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the Intereſt but of one Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in that Kingdom, and though he names <hi>Ireland</hi> often, he means the Native <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſt only. But I proceed</p>
            <p>To prove, that it is the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of the <hi>Britiſh,</hi> that <hi>Ireland</hi> ſhould be Governed by an <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh-man:</hi> I need ſay no more than that they all ardently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire it; and People are the beſt Judge of their own Neceſſities: The common Maxim that, <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt will not Lye,</hi> holds good here to ſome purpoſe. The ill effects the contrary method has had on their Perſons and Eſtates, is but too viſible. Whoever had ſeen <hi>Ireland</hi> four Years ago, and would compare its condition with what it is now, from the moſt thriving and flouriſhing Country of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> from a place of the briskeſt Trade, and beſt paid Rents in <hi>Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndom,</hi> it is fallen in one Year and a haſt's time, to Ruine and Deſolation: in the moſt fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented Cities, empty Houſes, and melancholy Countenances; in the beſt Peopl'd Counties, unma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nur'd neglected Fields, and Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarineſs: Such a one, I ſay, might juſtly exclaim, <hi>Heu! Quantum mutatus ab illo.</hi> But it would be impertinent to inſiſt any longer on this. I muſt now prove, That 'tis the advantage of the very Natives themſelves, (who have long been uneaſie under the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Government, and often en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd to ſhake it off) to be Rul'd and Guided by that Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they hate ſo much. They are beholding to us for reducing them from a ſtate of Barbarity, which left but little difference between them and Brutes: We taught them to Live, to Eat, Drink, and Lodge like humane Creatures; (if they eſteem this any advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and do not really prefer their Native Wildneſs to all the benefits of Civil Society, Trade, Agriculture, Merchandizing, Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) and if the gentleneſs of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government could have had any influence on them, they had no reaſon to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented at it: They had the equal Protection of the Laws, in relation to their Eſtates and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; they bore but their juſt proportion in all Taxes and Ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: Their Lands improv'd in va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48395:4"/>by the means of their <hi>Britiſh</hi> Neighbours, and their Rents were much better paid than former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, whilſt themſelves were Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the whole Iſland: They had a large connivance for the exerciſe of their Religion, and were even allowed to hold a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Synod of their own Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy in <hi>Dublin,</hi> Anno 1666: The poor Natives were not oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, when their ſevere Land-lords, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Gentry, by their cruel Extortions, Caſherings, Duties, and Days Labour ruin'd them; who as ſoon as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners prevailed among them, (as they were introduced with diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty enough, there was need of the Authority of Acts of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament to conſtrain them for their own good) lived plentifully, and in convenient Houſes, had their ſhare of the current Coyn, and proportion of all other Neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, to the life and well-being of Man, which now they want; inſomuch that ſeveral of them have been heard to Curſe my Lord <hi>Tyrconnel;</hi> for to his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment they attribute their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, and acknowledge, they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver liv'd ſo well as under the Lirection of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Rulers, nor expected to do ſo again, till they were reſtored to the Helm. See the force of Truth, which compels a confeſſion of it, even from the mouths of its Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries!</p>
            <p>One may eaſily perceive by our Author's manner of arguing, where the Shooe pinches; he is really concern'd that <hi>Ireland</hi> is not altogether an independent Kingdom, and in the hands of its own Natives: he longs till the day, when the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Yoak of Bondage ſhall be thrown off: Of this he gives us broad hints, when he tells us that, [<hi>England</hi> is the only Nation in the World that impedes their Trade:] That [a man of <hi>Engliſh</hi> intereſt will never Club with them (as he phraſes it) or Project any thing which may tend to their advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, that will be the leaſt bar, or prejudice to the Trade of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>] Now why a man of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> intereſt (unleſs he will allow none of that Nation to be an able and juſt Miniſter to his Prince) ſhould be partial, to ruine one Kingdom, [to avoid the leaſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniency of the other] con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the poſitive Commands of his King, I cannot imagine: For ſince [it is the Governour's Duty to Rule by Law, and ſuch Orders as he ſhall receive from His Majeſty] I know no grounds for our Author's Arraigning the whole <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, in ſaying, That no one man among them, of what Perſwaſion ſoever, will be true either to the Laws, or his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties poſitive Orders, which ſhall ſeem repugnant to the ſmalleſt conveniencies of <hi>England.</hi> This
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48395:4"/>is a glory reſerv'd only (as it ſeems) for his Hero, my Lord <hi>Tyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>connel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Imbargo upon the <hi>Weſt-India</hi> Trade, and the Prohibition of <hi>Iriſh</hi> Cattle, are the two Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces given.</p>
            <p>It were to be wiſhed indeed, for the good of that Kingdom, that both were taken off; and I que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion not but to ſee a day wherein it ſhall ſeem proper to the King, and an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Parliament, to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal thoſe Laws; a day wherein they will conſider us as their own Fleſh and Blood, a Colony of their Kindred and Relations, and take care of our Advantages with as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle grudging and repining (I am ſure they have the ſame and no ſtronger Reaſon) as <hi>Cornwall</hi> does at <hi>Yorkſhire:</hi> There are inſtances in ſeveral Iſlands in the <hi>Eaſt-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> as far diſtant as <hi>Ireland</hi> is from <hi>England,</hi> that make up but one Kingdom, and Govern'd by the ſame Laws; but the Wiſdom of <hi>England</hi> will not judge it time fitting to do this, till we of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> be one Man's Children, either in Reality or Affection; we wiſh the latter, and have made many ſteps and advances towards it, if the Natives will not meet us half way, we cannot help it, let the Event lie at their own Doors.</p>
            <p>But after all, I ſee not how thoſe Inſtances have any manner of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Chief Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours in <hi>Ireland;</hi> they were nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Cauſes, Contrivers, nor Promoters of thoſe Acts. The King and an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Parliament did it without conſulting them; if they had, 'tis forty to one, My Lord of <hi>Ormond</hi> and the Council, whoſe ſtake is ſo great in <hi>Ireland,</hi> would have hindered it as much as poſſible. Our Author's Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment proves indeed, That 'tis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimental to <hi>Ireland,</hi> to be a ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate Kingdom to <hi>England</hi> (and 'tis plain, 'tis that he drives at, let him diſguiſe it as much as he will) but the Concluſion he would prove, cannot at all be deduced from it: Shortly, I expect, he will ſpeak plainer, and in down right terms propoſe, That the two Kingdoms may be Governed by different Kings; Matters ſeem to grow ripe for ſuch a Diſloyal Propoſition.</p>
            <p>If theſe Acts (and not the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to an <hi>Engliſh</hi> King) were the Grievances, they would be ſo to the <hi>Britiſh</hi> there, as well as to the Natives: but tho' we wiſh them Repealed, we do not repine; in the mean time, if the <hi>Britiſh</hi> who are the moſt conſiderable Trading part of that Nation, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently feel the ill effects of thoſe Acts more ſenſibly, can be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, why the Natives ſhould not acquieſce in it, (unleſs it be for the forementioned Reaſons) I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee.</p>
            <p>Our Author allows that there are different ways of obeying the King: 'tis a Point gained for us,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48395:5"/>and proves there may be ſuch a partiality exerciſed in executing His Majeſty's Commands, as may deſtroy the very intent of them; and yet (taking the matter ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly [the King is obeyed] but a good Miniſter will conſider his Maſters intention, and not make uſe of a word that may have a double ſenſe to the ruine of a Kingdom, nor of a latitude of power, wherewith he is intruſted, to the deſtruction of the moſt conſiderable Party in it: Far be it from us to think it was His Majeſties Intention to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>populate a flouriſhing Country, to undo multitudes of laborious thri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Families in it, to diminiſh and deſtroy his own Revenue, to put the Sword into Mad-mens hands, who are ſworn Enemies to the Britiſh: No! His Majeſty, who is willing that liberty of Trade as well as Conſcience, ſhould equally flouriſh in all parts of his Dominions, that recommends him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to his Subjects by his imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality in diſtributing Offices of Truſt; and from that practice rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes his greateſt Argument to move his people to Repeal the Penal Laws; never intended that ſome general Commands of his ſhould be perverted to the deſtruction of that people, his intention is to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect. His Majeſty (Great as he is) cannot have Two Conſciences, one calculated for the Latitude of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> another for <hi>Ireland.</hi> We ought therefore to conclude, (in reſpect to the King) that His Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands have been ill underſtood, and worſe executed; and this may be done (as our Author con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes) and the King [undoubtedly obeyed] but ſuch an obedience is no better than a Sacrifice of the beſt Subjects the King has in this Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Our Author has given very good Reaſons why the Natives may be well content with their preſent Governour, but I cannot forbear laughing at thoſe he has found out to ſatisfie the poor <hi>Britiſh</hi> with: My Lord <hi>Tyrconnel</hi>'s moſt Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, Charitable, Engliſh Lady: His high ſounding Name <hi>Talbot,</hi> in great Letters, a Name that no leſs frightens the Poor Engliſh in <hi>Ireland,</hi> then it once did the <hi>French;</hi> a name which becauſe he is in poſſeſſion of, I will not diſpute his Title to, but I have been credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly informed, that he has no rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to that moſt Noble Family of <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> (though my Lord <hi>Tyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>connel</hi> preſumes to bear the ſame Coat of Arms): a Name in ſhort, which I hope will prove in time, <hi>Vox &amp; praeterea nihil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Second Reaſon is drawn from his [Education] We have heard (and it has never yet been contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted) that my Lord <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> from his Youth upwards, has con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly born Arms againſt the <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh:</hi> if our Author will aſſure us of the contrary, I am apt to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve his Excellency will give him
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48395:5"/>no thanks, who layes the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Merit upon the Baſis of his conſtant adherence to the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Party: What uſe of Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation can be drawn from this head by the <hi>Britiſh,</hi> is beyond my skill to comprehend.</p>
            <p>A third Reaſon is drawn from his Stake in <hi>England;</hi> the Author would do well to ſhew us, in what County this lies, that we may know where to find Repriſals here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after; for ſince he offers this for Our Security, 'tis fit we enquire into the Title and Value of the Land, before we give ſo valuable a Conſideration.</p>
            <p>Thus this great heap of ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Reaſons, together with a large Panegyrick upon his Excellency's fair Face and good Shapes, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling us by the by, how he [was not kill'd at <hi>Drogbeda,</hi> becauſe he run away,] is enough, and more than enough to demonſtrate, that [the <hi>Britiſh</hi> have not the leaſt cauſe to be dejected, becauſe they are ſufficiently ſecure]: But I will agree with the Author in this, That he ſeems to have been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by Heaven againſt the moſt critical occaſion, that ſhould hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen in this Age: reſerv'd as one of the Vials of GOD's Wrath to plague the People.</p>
            <p>'Tis well that [Self-preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is allowed by God and Man;] and ſince he tells us, we are [People of a contrary Intereſt,] he gives us right to provide for Our ſelves and our Families, as well as we may; 'tis like a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Aggreſſor: firſt he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares who are his Enemies, then gives them warning to put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into a poſture of defence. We are beholding to him for this hint, and, I hope, ſhall make the right uſe of it. 'Tis below me to take notice of the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the expreſſion of [an hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Man's loſing his Head in a Crowd,] and the nonſence of the other, [The moſt men bite at the ſtone, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] Dogs indeed uſe to do ſo with us; but this is only to let the World know what Country man our Author is, and it may be 'tis the cuſtom here for theſe Men to imitate thoſe more rational Creatures.</p>
            <p>Our Author ſeems ſenſible, that many hard things have been done, which occaſioned Clamours againſt the preſent Governour; tho' I think our Grievances (how intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable ſoever) have been born more ſilently, then any Peoples ſince the Creation: ſince I do not remember any one Pamphlet has hitherto come out, to repreſent them; ours being of that nature, as ſtupifies us, and takes away the uſe of the Tongue and Pen: <hi>Curae leves loquuntur, ingentes ſtupent:</hi> I ſay he is not willing this load of Calumny ſhould reſt on my Lord <hi>Tyrconnel,</hi> but caſts it all on His Majeſty, imagining that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect we bear, (and juſtly) to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48395:6"/>our King, ought to render us tongue-ty'd in relation to the Male-Adminiſtration of his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. But I have already ſhewn, how the King's Orders may be ſtretch'd, and perverted. The ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry beſt and moſt cautiouſly penn'd Laws have a double edge, and (if the executive power be lodged in ill hands) have the worſt effect, even to the puniſhment of Well-doers, and the encouragement of them that do ill; and I queſtion not, in the leaſt, but this is our Caſe, and as little doubt that our Grievances would be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs'd, did not one of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties moſt eminent Virtues in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe between us and His Grace, I mean his Conſtancy to His old Servants; and our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition is ſo much the more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable, that His Majeſty can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be a Father of His Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try without ſeeming to deſert His Miniſter; but 'tis to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped that at long running, the Groans of a diſtreſſed Nation will prevail over all private Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</p>
            <p>Whether the Employment His Majeſty has given my Lord <hi>Tyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>connel,</hi> has not prov'd the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the augmentation of his Fortune, (as our Author inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates it has not) ſhall neither prove the ſubject of this Diſcourſe, nor object of our Envy. I ſhall one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay, if the report be true, that my Lord owes all his Eſtate to the King's bounty, 'tis ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully done to rob His Majeſty of the Honour and Thanks due to him, by denying it; much leſs is it our buſineſs to find fault with the advancement of <hi>five Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations.</hi> In this point Authors differ, for ſome ſpeak of 55 at leaſt: if there had not been the greateſt partiality in the World ſhewed, we ſhould never have open'd our mouths: if in an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of about 9000 <hi>Engliſh,</hi> Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and Souldiers, there be not 200 left (in a Country where the <hi>Engliſh</hi> have ſo much cauſe to fear) and thoſe turn'd out, for the moſt part, without any cauſe aſſign'd, after the moſt ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominious diſgraceful manner i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginable, ſtript naked in the Field, their Horſes, Boots, Buff-coats, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> taken from them, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them Bills to receive ſo much Money in <hi>Dublin,</hi> as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted to half the value of their Equipage, and that not paid without Charge and Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance; have they not reaſon to fear? If in a Country, whoſe Government was perfectly in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> hands, ſo ſudden an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration was made, that both the Courts of Judicature, and Charters of their Corporations were taken from them without any fault of theirs, have they not reaſon to complain, and be affraid? If thoſe very Arms which are taken from them, be
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48395:6"/>put into the hands of their ſworn Enemies, and their juſt Debts paid after a new Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, by beating or killing the Creditors, when they demand their own, Have they not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to fear, and deſert the Kingdom? If theſe and an hundred other things do not juſtifie the retreat of ſeveral of the <hi>Britiſh</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> I know not what ſhall be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged a ſufficient Reaſon. This our Author would inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate is cauſed by a ſullen Combination; as if the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of a Nation could agree together to do a thing ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their viſible Intereſt, as deſert their Houſes and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, to the loſs of one half of them, meerly out of ſpite to the Government.</p>
            <p>But becauſe our Author is ſo good at his Narratives, and would induce the World to believe that there was but two Regiments disbanded [by his talking only of two] and in another place ſpeaking of [ſome Officers] that were Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiered. We ſhall hereafter give a faithful Account of the Proceedings in the buſineſs of Disbanding; und in the mean time affirm, That his whole Account of the Affair at <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingar</hi> is moſt unſincere. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Soldiers were given to underſtand, that they were all to be turned out, and the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Grace his Excellency did them, was to declare before a long and tedious March, That ſuch as had a mind or had Settlements in that Country might better quit then, than hereafter. This is plainly ſhewn by the turning out (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards) all thoſe <hi>Engliſh</hi> who then actually continued in the Service; they were glad that any would quit vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily, but thoſe that did not, and after a publick Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al were willing to ſerve His Majeſty, they ſoon after turn'd out. Thus the falſe gloſs that our Author puts upon my Lord <hi>Tyrconnel</hi>'s Speech is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd: And I aſſure the Reader the Memoires I have by me are from ſuch unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionable hands, and there are ſo many hundred living Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes to the truth of them, that our Author will not have the Impudence to deny what may be prov'd before His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, if he require it. I ſhall only take notice of the ill Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of our Author's Sea-Metaphor. Tho' in ſtreſs of Weather the Owner is willing to make uſe of all hands that may be helpful towards the ſaving the Veſſel, yet he takes care to call for none whoſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48395:7"/>practice it hath been to cut the Tacklings, and to ſteer contrary to the Pilot's Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; he thinks ſuch ſafer by far ſhut up under Hatches, then ſet at liberty or employ'd to do miſchief: As for his ſuppoſition of 30000 men to be ſent out of <hi>Ireland,</hi> into <hi>Flanders,</hi> I cannot tell what to make on't. Let them crack the Shell that hope to find a Kernel in it. For my part I deſpair: tho' the readineſs of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Soldiers of <hi>Ireland,</hi> who at twenty four hours warning came into <hi>England</hi> to ſerve His Majeſty in the time of <hi>Monmouth</hi>'s Rebellion, ought to have been remembred to their advantage, and might ſerve (to any unprejudic'd per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) as a Pattern of the Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, and good Inclinations of all the Proteſtants in that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, if His Majeſty had had occaſion for them. Whether the Parliament will Repeal the <hi>Teſt</hi> for thoſe ſeveral weighty Reaſons our Author ſays [are fitter for Contemplation then Diſcourſe] though methinks it would be pleaſant to ſee a Houſe of Commons ſit like the Brethren at a ſilent Meeting, is not my Province to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine: As likewiſe, Whether they will ſo much conſider that Grand Reaſon [the King will have it ſo] (for his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and theirs may differ) or what the Diſſenters will do, I cannot tell. One thing I am ſure of, there will be no ſuch Stumbling-block in the way of the King's deſires, when they meet, as the preſent conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Ireland;</hi> they will be apt (when his Majeſty tells them, they ſhall have their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall ſhares in Employments, when they have Repealed the Laws) to ſay, Look at <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> ſee what is done there, where the Spirit of Religion appears barefac'd! and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly compute what may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of us, when we have removed our own legal Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; Since they now leap o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thoſe Hedges, what may we expect when they are quite taken away!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Poynings</hi> Law is a great grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance to our Author, and here in one word, he diſcovers that 'tis the dependance this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom has on <hi>England,</hi> he quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels at: 'Tis fit the Reader ſhould underſtand, that Law (enacted when <hi>Poynings</hi> was Lord Deputy) makes all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Acts of Parliament of force in <hi>Ireland;</hi> we are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo fond of that Law, and covet ſo much to preſerve our dependance on <hi>England,</hi> that all the Arguments our Author
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48395:7"/>can bring, ſhall not induce us to part with it.</p>
            <p>I will not reflect in the leaſt on the Courage of the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> I know there are ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral brave men among them, but they have had the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune to fall under the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of (as our Author ſoftens it, but the plain ſence is, been Beaten by) a War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Nation: and, I queſtion not, unleſs they behave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves modeſtly in their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, they will again fall under the Conſideration of the ſame Nation: 'tis better we ſhould live in peace and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſs, but the Choice is in their hands, and if they had rather come under our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration again, than avoid it, let them look to the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence.</p>
            <p>Another Advantage which may accrue to <hi>Ireland</hi> by a Native, as Governour, our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor reckons up to be, <hi>His perſonal knowledge of the To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and their Harbourers, and his being thereby better capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated to ſuppreſs them.</hi> Mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious People would be apt to infer from this Suggeſtion, that his Excellency had occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion formerly to be familiar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acquainted with ſuch ſort of Cattle. I have heard in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, that one of our braveſt <hi>Engliſh</hi> Princes, <hi>Henry</hi> the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> during the extravagancies of his Youth, kept company with publick Robbers, and often ſhar'd both in the Danger and Booty: but as ſoon as the the Death of his Father made way for his Succeſſion to the Crown, he made uſe of his former acquaintance of their Perſons and Haunts, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to the extirpating and diſſolving the greateſt knot of High-way-men, that ever trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled <hi>England.</hi> My Lord there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (in imitation of this great Prince, no doubt) will make uſe of his Experience that way, to the ſame end: and I rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily aſſent to the Author, that no <hi>Engliſh</hi> Governour can be ſo fit to clear that Kingdom of Torĭes, and that for the ſame reaſons he gives us.</p>
            <p>There are two other Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages remaining; one is, His Excellency's having alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy made different Parties in that Kingdom, the objects of his love and hatred, let the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences of the one, or the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of the other be never ſo conſpicuous: Whether the <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh</hi> can draw any comfort from his Excellency's knowledge of them this way, is fit to be debated. The other is, The probability of his getting the Statute for benefit of Clergy
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48395:8"/>in favour of Cow-Stealers and Houſe-Robbers, Repealed; where, by the way, there is a ſevere Rebuke given to our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Prieſts for their ill pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Mercy to <hi>Iriſh</hi> Offenders: A fault I hope they will be no more guilty of.</p>
            <p>Whether theſe Advantages be ſo conſiderable as to move His Majeſty to continue a man (for other more weighty Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons) abſolutely deſtructive to this Kingdom, or whether ſome of them might not be performed by an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, His Majeſty is the only Judge: Only this I am ſure of, The King (if he were under a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Obligations to His Miniſter) has fully diſcharged them all, and has ſhewed himſelf to be the beſt of Maſters, in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo great and honourable an Employment to his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and continuing him in it ſo long, notwithſtanding the decreaſe of his own Revenue, and the other viſible bad ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of his Management; the Impoveriſhment of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, amounting to at leaſt two Millions of Money: and his Majeſty may be now at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty (without the leaſt imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of breach of promiſe to his Servant) to reſtore us to our former flouriſhing conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by ſending ſome <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nobleman among us, whoſe contrary methods will, no doubt, produce different ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects.</p>
            <p>To conclude, methinks the <hi>compariſon</hi> between His Majeſty and <hi>Phillip</hi> of <hi>Macedon,</hi> when he was drunk, is a little too familiar, not to ſay unmanner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and that between <hi>Antipater</hi> and my Lord <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> is as great a Complement to the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>But provided my Lord be commended, which was our Author's chief deſign, he cares not tho' the compariſon does not hold good in all points; 'tis enough that we know we are Govern'd by ſuch a Prince that neither practiſes ſuch Debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches himſelf, nor allows of them in his Servants. But we are not beholding to the Author for the knowledge of this, ſhould a Forreigner read his Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet, or get it interpreted to him, he would be apt (and with reaſon) to conclude, that His Majeſty as much reſembled <hi>Phillip</hi> in a Debauch, as my Lord <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> does ſober <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipater.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have now done with all that ſeems of any weight in our Author's Pamphlet; and can ſee nothing in his Poſtſcript that deſerves an Anſwer. All that I will ſay is, That his <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipes</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:48395:8"/>bear no proportion to our deſperate Diſeaſe, and he will prove not to be a Phyſitian, but a pretending Quack, who by ill applied Medicines will leave us in a worſe Condition then he found us.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude with telling you, That your Letter which encloſed the Pamphlet, whereof I have here given you my thoughts, was more than a Fortnight on the way, or elſe you had received this ſooner. I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Dublin, <date>1688.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>SIR, Your most humble Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
